Forest bathing is a term
coined in Japan in the 1980s.
Since then, we've learned it has
benefits beyond just the exercise.
In this video, we'll look at
some of those benefits,
and whether or not you
actually need to visit a forest
to experience them.
"Boosting Anticancer Immunity and
Natural Killer Cell Function with Forest Bathing"
Previously, I showed how exposure to
nature can have self-reported
psychological benefits, but
there was a dearth of data
on changes in objective measurements;
so, I was excited to see this paper
on the effects on levels of the
stress hormone cortisol in the saliva
of those partaking in
“forest bathing,” which just means
visiting a forest and
surrounding yourself by trees.
The level of cortisol in your
saliva is considered an indicator
of your stress level, and
after walking in a forest,
compared to walking in a city,
or even after just hanging out
in a forest compared to a city,
people’s salivary cortisol levels
were significantly lower.
But wait a second,
the same effect was found
before they went to the forest. Huh?
Forest bathing was associated with
significantly lower salivary cortisol
both before and after, compared
with visiting an urban area.
Therefore, it appears that just the
thought of going to spend the day
in the forest relieved stress.
So, when comparing the effects of
forest bathing versus urban visiting,
the anticipation placebo effect
may play a more important role
in influencing stress levels
than the actual experience
of being in the forest.
So, I was ready to dismiss it
as just another nebulous psychological
effect until...I read this.
Studies on the effects of forest
bathing on the immune function
showed that visiting a forest
can induce a significant increase
in the number and activity
of natural killer cells,
one of the ways our
body fights off cancer.
That got my attention.
It all started with this study.
Twelve men were taken on a long
weekend to walk in some forests,
and almost all of the subjects
(11 out of 12) showed higher
natural killer cell activity after
the trip, and not just a little—
about a 50% increase
compared to before the trip.
Now, just exercise can
affect immune function,
but they weren’t walking any extra;
they were just walking
in a forest instead.
Yeah, but they also were
taken on a trip somewhere,
introducing other variables.
So, how about randomizing
them to go on
some city trip versus
the forest trip.
And if there is some
special forest effect,
how long does the effect last?
Do you have to like walk
in the forest every day?
Before jumping into all that,
how about we first see
if it works in women too.
Same kind of set-up, and same
results: a significant boost
in natural killer cell activity
walking around in the woods.
And this time they went back a
week later to retest them,
and they were still up, though
after a month they came back down.
But hey, once a week should do it,
but it was a multiple-day trip.
Who has time to hang out in
forests all weekend, every weekend?
How about just a little day trip?
The title gives it all away.
Boom! Same thing! The same big jump
measured the day after the trip
compared to before and with
the same staying power.
Natural killer cell activity
still boosted a week later.
This suggests that if people
visit a suburban forest park
once a week on a day trip,
they may be able to maintain
the increased anti-cancer immunity.
OK, but I’m still not convinced.
How can you attribute the benefit
to the forest itself, when all
you have is before and after data?
To make the case that nature
had anything to do with it
you’d need a control group
that took the same kind of trip
but went to somewhere else instead.
And… here we go.
It turns out visiting a
forest, but not a city,
increases human natural
killer activity.
Here’s the forest data
just like before,
but nothing on a trip to
go walking in a city.
By the end of the forest trip,
the subjects experienced a boost of 80%
in NK activity after forest bathing,
compared to only a 10% bump
for the city walkers.
And both trips were matched for
physical activity, and alcohol,
and sleep—other things that
can affect immune function.
And so, here we go.
Confirmation of boosted immunity,
but only on the forest trip,
“indicating that forest bathing
does indeed enhance [natural
killer cell] activity.”
Moreover, they found that
the increased activity lasted
up to 30 days after the
trip. Check it out.
Still up a week later and
even a bit up a month later.
“This suggests that if people
visit a forest once a month,
they may be able to maintain increased
[natural killer cell] activity.”
OK, so, now that we know
that it’s a real effect,
the next question is, why?
What is it about forests
that gives us the boost?
And (you can imagine Big Pharma
thinking) can you make it into a pill?
We’ll find out next.
Studies on the effects of forest bathing---
a traditional practice in Japan
of visiting a forest and breathing
its air---have found it can induce
significant increases in the number
and activity of natural killer cells
that can last for as long as a month.
And because natural killer cells are one
of the ways your body fights cancer
by killing off tumor cells, the
findings suggest that forest visits
may have a preventive effect on
cancer generation and progression.
OK, but how? Why did the
forest environment increase
natural killer cell activity? What is
it about the forest environment?
One thought is that the boost may
be related to a reduction in stress.
If you measure the amount of adrenaline
flowing through people's systems,
did hanging out in a forest, but not
in a city, drop adrenaline levels down?
Yes, so that checks out, but drip some
adrenaline on human blood cells
in a Petri dish, and there does
not appear to be any effect.
The stress hormone, cortisol,
on the other hand,
dramatically suppresses
natural killer cell activity.
So maybe the forest led to less
stress, less cortisol, which released
the natural killer cells under its
thumb, and you get that big boost?
We know being surrounded by nature can
decrease levels of cortisol in our saliva,
but what about our bloodstream?
A significant drop after a single day
trip to the forest. But a week later
the cortisol was normalizing,
and the forest effects sometimes
appeared to last an entire month.
Anything else that could cause a
longer-term immune system change?
Maybe we've been missing
some of our old friends.
If you sample outdoor air, you can pick
up an abundance of microorganisms
floating around from the soil or water,
which are absent in indoor air
(which is dominated by organisms that
either live on us or trying to attack us).
So maybe on a day-to-day basis,
in terms of keeping our immune system
on ready alert, it might not be sufficient
to encounter only the biased microbes of
the modern synthetic indoor environment
that lacks some of the old friends,
and probably bears little resemblance
to the microbes we evolved to live with
over millions of years.
Or maybe it's the plants themselves.
Maybe it's the aroma of the forest.
Trees produce aromatic volatile
compounds called phytoncides like pinene,
which you can breathe into
your lungs in the forest.
But do these compounds actually
get into your bloodstream?
One hour in the woods and
you get like a 6-fold increase
in circulating pinene levels
circulating throughout your system.
OK, but to fully connect all the
dots, the phytoncides like pinene,
these tree essential oils
would have to then induce
human natural killer cell activity.
And guess what?
Phytoncides induce human
natural killer cell activity.
If you stick natural killer
cells in a Petri dish
with some unsuspecting leukemia
cells, your killers can wipe out
some of the cancer cells. But add
a whiff of cypress, white cedar,
eucalyptus, or pine and the
cancer cells don't stand a chance.
A combination of wood aromas
improved the recovery of mice
put through the wringer, but this
is the study I was looking for.
If we want to know
if the magic ingredient
is the fragrance of the forest,
then let's see if we can get that same
boost in natural killer cell activity
just vaporizing some essential
oil from one of the trees
into a hotel room overnight.
And it worked! A significant boost
in natural killer cell activity, though
it just boosted their activity
rather than their number, and being
in the actual forest can do both.
So maybe it's a combination
of the tree fragrance and the lower
cortisol levels working together?
Ironically, these phytoncide compounds
are part of the tree's own immune system,
which we may be able to commandeer.
The researchers speculate these
compounds may be playing some role
in the fact that more heavily forested
regions in Japan appeared to have
lower death rates from breast
cancer and prostate cancer.
Being out in nature has been found
to be an important coping strategy
among cancer patients. It turns out
this could potentially be helping more
than just with the coping,
thanks to the fragrance of trees.